Guide to the Kenelm Henry Digby Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Kenelm Henry Digby collection
1815-1918
OSB MSS 81
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.41
(1 box)
The collection contains letters from various Digby family members and friends, including Marcella Digby; the comte d'Esgrigny; Henry Edward, Cardinal Manning; Montalembert; and Robert Hare. Letters from Ambrose Lisle Phillipps discuss Catholicism in England, recent conversions, and the early Oxford Movement; letters from Charles Julius Hare comment unfavorably on Digby's attacks on Protestantism. There is also a small amount of research correspondence with Bernard Holland, author of Memoir of Kenelm Henry Digby (1919). The collection also includes newspaper clippings of reviews of Digby's later works; obituaries of Digby; and a sketchbook.
Digby, Kenelm Henry, 1800-1880
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 2002
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
KENELM HENRY DIGBY, 1800-1880
Kenelm Henry Digby, youngest son of William Digby, Anglican Dean of Clonfert, was born in Ireland in 1800 and took his B.A. at Trinity College, Cambridge in 1819. In 1822 he published The Broad Stone of Honour, a lengthy but popular and influental work on chivalry.
Digby converted to Roman Catholicism in 1825 and published a much rewritten version of Broad Stone in 1826-27. Mores Catholici, an eleven-volume work on medieval Catholicism and culture, appeared in 1831-40, and Compitum, or, The Meeting of the Ways at the Catholic Church, a Catholic apologetic, in 1848. In addition to these, Digby published several collections of poetry; the meditative The Lover's Seat (1856); The Chapel of St. John, or, A Life of Faith in the Nineteenth Century (1861), dedicated to his late wife; and Evenings on the Thames, or, Serene Hours and What They Require (1864).
Digby married Jane Mary Dillon in 1833; the couple had seven children, one of whom, Marcella Digby, was received into the Convent of the Sacred Heart at Roehampton in 1859 against her father's wishes. The Digbys spent much time in France during the 1840s and 1850s. After Jane Digby's death in 1860, Digby led an increasingly retired life at his home in Kensington until his own death on March 22, 1880.
Scope and Contents
The Kenelm Henry Digby Collection consists of papers relating to the faith and literary career of Kenelm Henry Digby, possibly collected by Bernard Holland in the course of his research for Memoir of Kenelm Henry Digby (1919). The collection has been organized into two series: Series I. Correspondence, and Series II, Other Papers. The papers span the dates 1815-1918.
Series I, Correspondence, spans the years 1815-1918 and is organized into two subseries: Digby Family Correspondence and Research Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
The first subseries, Digby Family Correspondence, contains a few letters by members of Digby's family, including his brother Richard and his daughter Marcella, who speaks of their shared faith and her life as a nun in Chile. There is also a letter from Hubert Dormer to his future wife Mary Digby discussing plans for the couple to live with Digby after their marriage. A few correspondents are represented only by letters of condolence written on the death of Digby, including Edward John Tilt and Cardinal Manning.
In addition to these, there are letters to Digby from various friends, in particular the comte d'Esgrigny, whom Digby and his family visited many times. The letters in the collection date from the last years of Digby's life and contain family and personal news; wishes for Digby's improved health; and comments on faith and the political situation of the Catholic Church in France.
The fourteen letters from Ambrose Lisle Phillipps contain much discussion of English Catholic teachings and practices; news of and reflections on the early progress of what came to be known as the Oxford Movement; reports on Movement figures such as Wiseman, Newman, and Manning; and commentary on the increase in conversions among the English and the popular and political reactions against them.
Other friends represented in the collection include Robert Hare, George Spencer, and the Anglican Julius Charles Hare, who in two 1842 letters expresses his anger at Digby's "virulent bigotry" against Protestantism in general and the Church of England in particular. There is also one 1858 letter to Digby from Montalembert, in English, praising his Lover's Seat.
The second subseries, Research Correspondence, consists of letters to Bernard Holland written in response to his requests for information on Digby's life. Folder 31 contains a biographical sketch of his daughter Marcella, which was enclosed in a letter to Holland. There are also letters from his publisher concerning publication details.
Series II, Other Papers, is housed in folders 39-45 and contains newspaper clippings relating to various works by Digby; obituary notices for him; one folder of research notes; and a sketchbook holding a variety of landscape drawings in pencil and ink.
Anglo-Catholicism; Catholics -- England; English prose literature -- 19th century; Oxford movement; Authors; Digby, Kenelm Henry, 1800-1880; Digby, Marcella; Hare, Julius Charles, 1795-1855; Holland, Bernard, 1856-1926; Jouenne d'Esgrigny d'Herville, Marie François Jules de; Manning, Henry Edward, 1808-1892; Montalembert, Charles Forbes, comte de, 1810-1870; Phillipps, Ambrose Lisle, 1809-1878
- Correspondence, 1815-1918; Series I; 0.30' (0.75 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries and arranged alphabetically by correspondent within each.
  - DIGBY FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Arundel and Surrey, Countess of
      - ALS to David Lewis, [1849 Mar] (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Inviting the recipient and "Mr. Newman"(John Henry Newman?) to Easter dinner
    - de Bistolli, G.; Paris
      - ALS to [KHD], 1845 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Digby, B.
      - ALS to KHD, 1842 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Digby, Kenelm Henry, 1800-1880
      - ALS draft to "My dear mother", 1815 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 2 ALS to "Madame la Baronne d'Erval", 1822, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Digby, Marcella
      - ALS to KHD; Valparaiso, Chile, 1879 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Digby, Richard, d. 1820
      - ALS to "My dear mother", 1817 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dormer, Hubert
      - ALS to Mary Digby Dormer, 1865 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        On her acceptance of his proposal
    - Hare, Julius Charles, 1795-1855
      - 2 ALS to KHD, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hare, Robert, 1781-1858
      - ALS to KHD; Winkfield Park, n.y. Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jouenne d'Esgrigny d'Herville, L.
      - 7 ALS to KHD, 1878-80, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Jouenne d'Esgrigny d'Herville, Marie François Jules de
      - 29 ALS to KHD, 1876-80, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
        With: ALS to Hubert Dormer, 1880 Mar 25, on the death of KHD
    - La Bourdennaye de Blossac, comte de
      - ALS to KHD; Hotel de la Varenne, n.y. Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Manning, Henry Edward, 1808-1892
      - ALS to Mary Digby Dormer; Westminster, 1880 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        On the death of KHD
    - Molesworth, B.
      - ALS to Mary Digby Dormer; Monastery of St Ann, [1880 Mar] (Box 1, Folder 19)
        On the death of KHD Also signed: "Teresa of Jesus"
    - Montaigu, M. de
      - 3 ALS to KHD, 1870-79, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
        With: ALS to Hubert Dormer, 1880 Mar 31, on the death of KHD
    - Montalembert, Charles Forbes, comte de, 1810-1870
      - ALS to KHD; Athenaeum Club, 1858 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Praising The Lover's Seat
    - Murray, E.
      - ALS to KHD, 1826 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Phillipps, Ambrose Lisle, 1809-1878
      - 14 ALS to KHD, 1827-42 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
    - Shadwell, Cayley
      - 2 ALS to KHD; Upper Gower Street, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Spencer, George, 1799-1864
      - ALS to KHD; St. Mary's Abbey, 1841 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Tilt, Edward John, 1815-1893
      - ALS to Hubert Dormer; 27 Seymour St, Portman Square, 1880 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - RESEARCH CORRESPONDENCE
    - Butler, Henry Montagu, 1822-1918
      - 2 ALS to Bernard Holland; Trinity College, Cambridge, 1916 Jul (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Enclosure: TLS from W. W. Rouse Ball to Butler, 1916 Jul 10
    - D'Arcy, M.
      - ALS to Bernard Holland; Convent of the Sacred Heart, Roehampton, 1916 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        With "Madame Marcella Digby," biographical sketch, in French, of KHD's daughter
    - Digby, John
      - ALS to Geta Dormer; 43 St. Georges Road, 1916 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - ALS to Bernard Holland; 43 St. Georges Road, 1916 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dormer, Geta [Gertrude]
      - 6 ALS to Bernard Holland, 1916 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Dormer, May
      - 2 ALS to Bernard Holland, 1916 Jul (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Longman, Thomas Norton, 1849-1930
      - 4 TLS to Bernard Holland, 1918 Jul-Oct (Box 1, Folder 36)
        With: publication contract for Memoir of Kenelm Henry Digby from Longmans, Green, and Co., 1918 Oct 2
    - Palmer, Aidan, O.S.P.
      - 3 ALS to Bernard Holland, 1916 Jul (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Empty envelopes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Other Papers, 1856-1880; Series II; 0.10' (0.25 box)
  Series II, Other Papers, is arranged alphabetically by type of material,
  - Newspaper clippings, 1856-58 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Notebook containing mainly reviews of The Lover's Seat
  - Newspaper clippings, 1858-63 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Notebook containing mainly reviews of The Children's Bower and The Chapel of St. John
  - Newspaper clippings, 1860-72 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Notebook containing reviews of Evenings on the Thames and several collections of poems by KHD
  - Newspaper clipping, 1877 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Essay on The Broad Stone of Honour from The Morning Post
  - Newspaper clippings, 1880 Mar (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Obituary notices for KHD
  - Research notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sketchbook, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Landscape sketches in pencil and ink by an unidentified artist